Finding Aid for Mothers Against Drunk Driving, Michigan Chapter, Records, 1982-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mothers Against Drunk Driving, Michigan Chapter, Records 1982-1994
Mothers Against Drunk Driving. Michigan Chapter.
(in 10 boxes)
9 linear feet
8926 Bk 2
Records of the MADD's state coordinating council, files from the various county chapters, bulletins from the national headquarters of MADD, and programs and clippings describing state activities; also videotapes relating to the work of the organization, and audio-tapes promoting the organization and its aims.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 7590 ) was originally deposited by the executive director of MADD, August 1988. Additional deposits were made in October 1991 and January 1995.
The record group is open to research except for State Coordinating Committee Correspondence (boxes 8-10) which is closed to researchers except with the written permission of the executive director.
Mothers Against Drunk Driving (MADD) is a nationwide nonprofit organization of women and men dedicated to reducing the number of alcohol and other drug-related traffic accidents and to supporting the victims of accidents caused by impaired driving. Founded in California in 1980 by Candy Lightner, the mother of a teenage hit-and-run victim, MADD chapters have organized across the country, usually at the county level. A state coordinating committee (SCC), comprised of one representative from each county chapter, coordinates an information-sharing network throughout the state. As a "grassroots" organization, MADD emphasizes working on a local level, and national programs are implemented by the county chapters, with the guidance of the SCC. These programs include public awareness campaigns, youth education, victim services and working toward tougher anti-impaired driver legislation and regulations.
Organization of MADD chapters in Michigan began with a steering group in February 1982. The Wayne County chapter functioned as both local and state headquarters under the leadership of Lee Landes. In 1986, all state coordinating functions were transferred to the Midland County Chapter. Bethany Goodman, a founding member of the Midland Chapter, was hired as Executive Director of MADD, Michigan and the organization entered a new, more professionalized era.
During these years, over twenty additional county chapters were chartered throughout the state. Chapter guidelines, fundraising advisories, and publicity materials were provided for each new chapter by the State of Michigan Coordinating Committee. The Michigan SCC changed its name to the Michigan State Organization in May 1991. This body meets three times annually and in addition to new chapter business, hears from several subcommittees, including Executive, Legislative, and Finance. Although the policies and materials developed by the state organization must not conflict with those of the national organization, the Michigan State Organization has maintained a certain autonomy.
Among the more notable programs sponsored by MADD, Michigan are the statewide candlelight vigils held each December to remember those who have lost their lives in alcohol-related traffic accidents. Two other Holiday-oriented programs are the free taxi service known as "LifeRide," which is co-sponsored by MADD and other civic/business organizations in several Michigan cities on New Year's Eve, and Project Red Ribbon, which urges community members to tie red ribbons on his or her car to show commitment to driving sober. In recent years MADD has developed more programs geared toward educating youth about the dangers of drinking and driving, including Keep It A Safe Summer (KISS) and a Poster/Essay contest for students in grades 1-12. MADD, Michigan also holds various workshops in order to form coalitions with other groups. They have also implemented Victim Impact Panels, providing a forum for convicted drunk drivers to hear victims tell their stories.
The records of Mothers Against Drunk Driving (MADD), Michigan are divided into eight series: State Coordinating Committee Files; Outreach Programs, Panels And Workshops; Publicity And Publications; Topical Files; County Chapter Files; Visual Materials; Sound recordings; and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Drinking and traffic accidents--Michigan.; Drunk driving--Michigan.; Mothers Against Drunk Driving (Organization). Michigan Chapter.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Social reformers--Michigan.; Women social reformers--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Demonstrations.; Drunk driving--Michigan.; Mothers Against Drunk Driving (Organization). Michigan Chapter.; Vigils.; Women.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Mothers Against Drunk Driving (Organization). Michigan Chapter.; Mothers Against Drunk Driving (Organization). Grand Traverse County Chapter.; Drinking and traffic accidents--Michigan.; Drunk driving--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- State Coordinating Committee files 1982-1993
  State Coordinating Committee Files contain materials generated by the initial steering committee and the SCC/Michigan State Organization. This series includes policies and guidelines, reports, financial papers, minutes, and legislative lobbying files.
  - MADD, National Policies and Guidelines for Local and State Organizations 1983-1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Policies, Guidelines and Position Descriptions 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Chart (Box 1)
  - Lists of Chapter Contacts 1982-1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Executive Director's Reports 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Agendas 1982-1993, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Subcommittees
    - Budget and Finance Committee Minutes 1990, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1987-1993 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee and Budget and Finance Committee Joint Minutes 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee and Legislative Committee Joint Minutes 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Legislative Committee Minutes 1987-1992 (Box 1)
    - Legislative Committee Correspondence 1987-1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Scholarship Committee Minutes 1991 (Box 1)
  - Financial Papers 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - Audited Financial Statements 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Legislation Supported by MADD, Michigan 1982 (Box 1)
  - Legislation Supported by MADD, Michigan 1985 (Box 1)
- Outreach Programs, Panels and Workshops 1982-1993
  Outreach Programs, Panels and Workshops includes materials about the programs MADD, Michigan implements at the chapter level to raise community awareness of the dangers of drinking and driving. Some are one time events, like the "Bridging the Gap" workshop with the Michigan Sheriffs' Association, and some, like the candlelight vigil, are annual events.
  - Action Workshop 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bridging the Gap Workshop 1989 (Box 1)
  - Candlelight Vigil Program 1982-1985, 1988-1989, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Drive For Life Program 1987-1990, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Drunk Driving Victim Impact Panel 1990 (Box 1)
  - Impaired Driving Issues Workshop 1990 (Box 1)
  - Keep it a Safe Summer (KISS) Program 1989-1992, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Kelly and Company Television Show Appearance 1987 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Conference 1987 (Box 1)
  - Liferide Program 1983-1986, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - National Crime Victims and Volunteer Recognition Week 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Operation/C.A.R.E. Program 1992 (Box 2)
  - Operation Prom/Graduation Program 1986, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Poster/Essay Contest 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Professional Advisory Panel of State Safety Commission 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Project Graduation 1990 (Box 2)
  - Project Red Ribbon 1987-1992, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Safe Rides Workshop 1986 (Box 2)
  - Victim Assistance Service Program 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Publicity and Publications 1982-1994
  Publicity and Publications includes hardcopy of the newsletter of MADD, Michigan, a quarterly publication sent out to all members. There are also two computer disks that contain copies of newsletters and a file of photographs used in the newsletters. This series includes press releases, PSAs, position statements, letters to the editor and newsclippings, as well as a file of promotional items.
  - Newsletters on Disks 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Photographs used in Newsletters (Box 2)
  - Position Statements 1982-1991, undated (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, PSAs, Media Alerts 1984-1992, undated, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters to the Editor 1988-1992 (Box 2)
  - Promotional Material (Box 2)
  - Newsclippings (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1984-1992
  Topical Files include the controversial McKinsey Report, concerning the "continued success" of the national organization, and "strategic planning" correspondence among the executive directors of several states. There are files of information about former Representative Dennis Dutko, about the fight against AAA's insurance reform proposal and the results of surveys of political candidates taken in 1988 and 1990. A sampling of the returned surveys was retained. There is a small amount of information about two groups "related" to MADD; Students Against Driving Drunk (SAAD) and Drinkers Against Mad Mothers (DAMM)
  - Drinkers Against Mad Mothers (D.A.M.M.) 1984 (Box 2)
  - McKinsey Report on MADD National 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Political Candidate Survey 1988, 1990, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Proposal "D", AAA's Insurance Reform Proposal 1992 (Box 3)
  - Representative Dennis Dutko 1989 (Box 3)
  - State Executive Directors 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Students Against Driving Drunk (S.A.D.D.), Michigan, Newsletter 1987 (Box 3)
- County Chapter Files 1982-1992
  County Chapter Files contain a wide variety of recorded information generated by the county chapters chartered in Michigan. Materials in this series include correspondence between the SCC and the chapters, chapter bulletins, announcements, and newsletters highlighting the activities of each individual chapter, and newsclippings pertaining to MADD's involvement with the local community. In addition, several county chapter files include information on special programs enacted in a specific county. The Midland County Victims Assistance file, in particular, is an excellent example of a support program sponsored by the county chapters of MADD.
  - Barry County
    - 1987-1992, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Bay County
    - 1985-1990 (Box 3)
  - Benzie County
    - 1985-1989 (Box 3)
  - Calhoun County
    - 1987-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Cass County
    - 1987-1992, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Charlevoix County
    - 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Chippewa County
    - 1985-1992, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Dickinson County
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Genesee County
    - 1987-1992, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Grand Traverse County
    - 1986-1992, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Ingham County
    - 1987-1992, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Tom Rollins File (1989-1991) (Box 3)
  - Ionia County
    - 1989-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Jackson County
    - 1987-1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo County
    - 1985-1992, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Kent County
    - 1985-1992, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Alternative Detention Facility Material 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Court Watchers Report 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Lapeer County
    - 1988-1992, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Livingston County
    - 1984-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Macomb County
    - 1984-1992, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Marquette County
    - 1985 (Box 4)
  - Mason County
    - 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Midland County
    - 1984-1991, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - Board Minutes 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    - General Material (Box 5)
    - Victims Assistance Packet (Box 5)
  - Monroe County
    - 1985 (Box 5)
  - Muskegon County
    - 1985-1989 (Box 5)
  - Oakland County
    - 1986-1992, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Newsclippings (Box 5)
  - Saginaw County
    - 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - St. Clair County
    - 1983-1986 (Box 5)
  - Tri-County (Ingham, Eaton and Clinton)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County
    - 1983-1992, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Wayne County
    - 1984-1992, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Board Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters 1982-1991, undated (Box 5)
    - General Materials 1986 (Box 5)
    - Reports-Annual, Administrative and Financial 1988-1991 (Box 5)
    - Press Releases, Media Alerts and Statements 1986-1991, undated (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1988-1991, 15 folders (Box 6)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes videotapes of local and national television programs about the work of the organization and a feature length television motion picture. There are also four posters including three winners of the poster/essay contest.
  - Videotapes (U-matic) 1982-1985
    - 1982
      - WJBK-TV 2, "Face-to-Face" March 13, 1982 (Box 7)
      - CBS News-Charles Kuralt May 4, 1982 (Box 7)
    - 1983
      - "The Candy Lightner Story," part 1 March 13, 1983 (Box 7)
      - "The Candy Lightner Story", part 2 (Box 7)
      - Hou-TV (Houston, TX), "Nancy Carney Show" March 20, 1983 (Box 7)
    - 1984
      - WDIV-TV 4, "Mort Crim and Editorial" March 15, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Michigan Association of Police (Public Service Announcement) December 4, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Phil Donahue Show with Presidents of Coors and Stroh Brewery Co. (Box 7)
    - 1985
      - WJBK-TV 2, "MADD Update" September 22, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Videotapes (VHS) 1985-1992
    - 1985
      - WTVS-TV 56, "Dramshop Legislation" August 13, 1985 (Box 7)
      - WXYZ-TV 7, "Mother Forgives Killer" August 21, 1985 (Box 7)
    - 1992
      - Coalition for "Michigan Deserves Better" Press Conference [Against "Proposal D"] October 6, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Posters
    - 3 winners from the annual poster/essay contest (Box 7)
    - 1 promotional poster (Box 7)
- Sound Recordings, 1983-1984, undated
  The Audiocassettes includes a promotional tape, a recording of a candlelight vigil and of a Grand Traverse County Chapter Board Meeting.
  - 1983
    - "LifeRide" promotional tape December 1983 (Box 7)
  - 1984
    - Candlelight Vigil December 1984 (Box 7)
  - Undated
    - Grand Traverse County Chapter Board Meeting (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1982-1993 (Box 8)
    The correspondence is closed for research except with the written permission of the executive director of MADD, Michigan
  - Correspondence 1982-1993 (Box 9)
    (continued)
  - Correspondence 1982-1993 (Box 10)